Guide to the David Ludlow Thompson Papers 1862-1961 (Bulk 1862-1865) MS 670.24
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
The David Ludlow Thompson Papers
1862-1961 (Bulk 1862-1865)
MS 670.24
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.7 Linear feet (2 boxes)
The David Ludlow Thompson Papers consist primarily of letters Thompson sent to his mother, Keturah Sayre Thompson, and his friend, Elias A. Fairchild, relating his experiences in battle during the American Civil War, inquiring about friends and relations at home, and asking to be sent clothing, food, and reading materials. Housed with each letter is a transcript provided by the donor that has been photocopied onto archival quality paper. The reader is cautioned against editorial mistakes in the transcripts. The "original" transcripts (i.e. those not printed on archival quality paper) are housed in a binder in Box 2, along with a wooden spoon carved by Thompson while he was held as a prisoner of war. Portions of this collection relating to the Civil War have been digitized and are available to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical Note
David Ludlow Thompson was born in Windham, Ohio on August 28, 1837 and was educated at the Flushing Institute in Flushing, Long Island, where he became a faculty member.
In August of 1862, he enlisted in the Ninth New York Volunteer Infantry, Company G (also known as Hawkins' Zouaves), and was later transferred to the Third New York Volunteer Infantry, Company B. During his war service, Thompson saw action in the Peninsular Campaign, the Battle of Antietam, and the siege of Charleston. He was taken as a prisoner of war by the Confederate troops after Antietam and was held at Libby Prison in Richmond, Virginia for 18 days before being exchanged. In 1863, he spent time in an army hospital in Portsmouth, Virginia.
David Ludlow Thompson was honorably discharged from military service on June 17, 1865 and died on March 31, 1926.
Scope and Content Note
The David Ludlow Thompson papers consist primarily of letters that Thompson wrote to his mother, Keturah Sayre Thompson, and his friend, Elias A. Fairchild, describing army life, relating his experiences in battle, inquiring about friends and relations at home, and asking to be sent clothing, food, and reading materials. His letters also include detailed descriptions of the weather, the inedible rations, the ill-fitting garments provided by the U.S. Sanitary Commission, his poor attempts to mend his clothing, his bout with scurvy, and having to share his quarters with rodents and insects. His advanced education is evident in his frequent references to the literary canon, using quotes from Milton, Chaucer, and Tennyson to illustrate different situations.
Most notably, the letters include a description of the Battle at Antietam and a letter sent to Elias A. Fairchild, declaring that David Ludlow Thompson had been declared a prisoner of war after Antietam.
Also included in the collection are photocopies of articles written by Thompson regarding his experiences during the American Civil War, biographical information, and a wooden spoon that Thompson carved while being held at Libby Prison in Richmond, Virginia.
Portions of this collection relating to the Civil War have been digitized and are available to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Arrangement
The David Ludlow Thompson papers are organized in the following six series:
Series 1: Letters sent by David Ludlow Thompson to Keturah Sayre Thompson, 1863-1865
Series 2: Letters sent by David Ludlow Thompson to Elias Fairchild, 1862-1865
Series 3: Letters sent by David Ludlow Thompson addressed jointly to Keturah Sayre Thompson, Elias Fairchild, and other family members, 1863-1865
Series 4: Other correspondence pertaining to David Ludlow Thompson, 1862-1865
Series 5: Biographical and Geneaological Materials, 1961, undated
Series 6: Wooden spoon made by David Ludlow Thompson, 1862
Fairchild, Elias A., 1827-1907; Thompason, Keturah Sayre, 1801-1888; Thompson, Keturah Sayre, 1801-1888; Antietam, Battle of, Md., 1862--Personal Narratives.; Correspondence; Libby Prison.; South Carolina--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Thompson, Keturah Sayre.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Hospitals.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal Narratives.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Prisoners and Prisons.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States.--Army.--New York Infantry Regiment, 9th (1861-1863).; United States.--Army.--Regiment Infantry, New York Volunteers, 3rd (1861-1865).; Virginia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1779-1851
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains correspondence between David Ludlow Thompson and his mother, Keturah Sayre Thompson. He writes primarily of the daily particulars of army life and asks often for news, clothing, and reading materials from home.
  - Letter sent by David Ludlow (D.L.) Thompson to Keturah Sayre (K.S.) Thompson, January 5, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, February 2, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, February 10, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, March 7, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, March 29, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, April 15, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, August 20, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, 1863 August (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, July 15, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, September 30, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, October 11, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, December 21-25, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, December 28, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, January 3, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, January 6-17, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, February 19-23, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, March 3, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, June 6, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to K.S. Thompson, June 9, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series 2: Letters sent by David Ludlow Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, 1862-1865
  Series 2 consists of letters sent by Thompson to his friend Elias Fairchild detailing the particulars of army life and asking for news from home. Most notably, this series contains a letter written from Libby Prison in October of 1862, detailing Thompson's experiences at the Battle of Antietam.
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, 1862 October (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, October 9, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, October 20, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, January 20, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, February 21, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, March 7, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, March 7, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, April 22, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, July 27, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, July 29, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, October 4, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, October 25, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, November 11, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, April 6, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Letter sent by D.L. Thompson to Elias A. Fairchild, June 3, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Series 3: Letters sent by David Ludlow Thompson addressed jointly to Keturah Sayre Thompson, Elias A. Fairchild, and other family members, 1863-1865
  Series 3 consists of letters addressed jointly to Keturah Sayre Thompson, Elias Fairchild, and occasionally other family members, including Thompson's sister. While Thompson again asks for news of home and describes the daily ritual of army life in these letters, he also describes his own bout with scurvy near the end of the war. Most notably, this series includes a letter written in August of 1863 from a military hospital in Portsmouth, Virginia describing his experiences there.
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, March 19, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, April 28, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, June 7, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, June 23, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, July 12, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, August 14, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, September 9, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, October 5, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, November 5, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, December 9, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, December 31, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, January 20, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, March 22, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, May 24, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, May 7,1864 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, May 15, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, June 8, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, August 29, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, February 7, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, February 16, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, March 27, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Joint letter sent by D.L. Thompson, April 26, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Series 4: Other correspondence pertaining to David Ludlow Thompson, 1862-1865
  Series 4 consists of the discharge papers of David Ludlow Thompson, two pieces of correspondence sent to Thompson, a letter sent to Elias A. Fairchild declaring Thompson to be a prisoner of war, and the fragments of several letters written by Thompson.
  - Discharge papers of David Ludlow Thompson, June 6, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Letter sent to Elias Fairchild, October 10, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Letter sent to D.L. Thompson, October 13, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Letter sent to D.L. Thompson, July 28, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Fragment of letter written by D.L. Thompson, September 1, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Fragment of letter written by D.L. Thompson, November 21, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Fragment of letter written by D.L. Thompson, June 17, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Series 5: Biographical and Genealogical Materials, 1961, undated
  Series 5 consists of biographical information about David Ludlow Thompson, including copies of articles he published about his experiences at Antietam and his obituary. This series also contains a 1961 letter from the U.S. Department of the Interior outlining his military record at the request of his grandson.
  - Biographical Information, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Copies of articles written by David Ludlow Thompson, Undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Series 6: Wooden spoon carved by David Ludlow Thompson, 1862
  Series 6 consists of a wooden spoon that was carved by David Ludlow Thompson while he was held prisoner at Libby Prison in Richmond, Virginia after the Battle of Antietam.
  - Wooden spoon carved by D.L. Thompson, 1862 (Box 2)